Guide to the Peninsular War letters, 1808-1814 MS 155
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Peninsular War letters
1808-1814
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Tulloh, William; Trant, Nicholas, Sir; Raglan, FitzRoy James Henry Somerset, Baron; Patrick, R. M.; Great Britain. Army
MS 155
0.1 Linear Feet (1 folder)
A collection of letters written by British officers serving in Portugal during the Peninsular War referring to matters concerning the war.
Historical Sketch
The Peninsular War took place in Spain and Portugal (1808-1814) during the Napoleonic Wars. When the French invaded Spain in 1808, an alliance formed between Spain, Portugal and Britain to expel the French Empire from the Iberian Peninsula.
Scope and Contents
A collection of letters written by British officers serving in Portugal during the Peninsular War referring to matters concerning the war. Among the writers are Lord Fitzroy Somerset, Colonel Trant, Major R. M. Patrick, Major William Tulloh, and Major Williams. Recipients include Marshal William Carr Beresford, Lieutenant-Colonel Robert Arbuthnot, and Lieutenant-Colonel Henry Hardinge. Also included in the collection is a memorandum to the Minsistre de la guerre re. candidates and a Military chart (22 April 1808).
Access Restriction
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Edwards (dealer) on June 18, 1963.
General note
Portions of this collection are available online at https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/21919.
Index Terms
Subjects
War; Soldiers; Peninsular War (1807-1814); Military
Document Types
corrrespondence
Places
Portugal; Great Britain; Spain
- Series I: Letters, 1808-1814, 8218
  - April 3, 1809; Coimbra; from Baron d Eben Comb; to "Sir", 8242 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - April 4, 1809; Thomar; from Jose de Miranda Henrique; to ?, 8241 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - April 5, 1809; Villa Leal; from Major Patrick; to Marshal Beresford, 8240 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - April 5, 1809; Coimbra; from Colonel Trant; to Marshal Beresford, 8239 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - April 5, 1809; Coimbra; from Colonel Trant; to "Sir", 8238 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - April 8, 1809; Villa Leal; from Major Patrick; to Marshal Beresford, 8237 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - April 10, 1809; Ageda; from Colonel Trant; to Marshal Beresford, 8236 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - April 13, 1809; Amarante; from Lt. Col. Patrick; to Marshal Beresford, 8235 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - June 28, 1811; Quinta de Joao; from F. Somerset; to Lt. Col. Hardinge, 8234 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aug 6, 1811; Penamacor; from F. Somerset; to Lt. Col. Hardinge, 8233 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aug 14, 1811; Gallegos; from G.B. Bingham; to Blachrie, 8232 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aug 25, 1811; Mafra; from Br. Gen. Blunt; to Lt. Col. Hardinge, 8231 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aug 27, 1811; Fucate; from Guinaldo F. Somerset; to Lt. Col. Hardinge, 8230 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Oct 27, 1811; Lisbon; from Lt. Col. Arbuthnot; to F. Somerset, 8229 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Oct 28, 1811; Lisbon; from Lt. Col. McIntosh; to Maj. Gen Peocock, 8228 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nov 1, 1811; Lisbon; from Michael Fitzpatrick; to Marshal Beresford, 8227 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nov 1, 1811; Freneda; from F Somerset; to Lt. Col. Arbuthnot, 8226 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nov 2, 1811; Elaos; from Major Tulloh; to Lt. Col. Arbuthnot, 8225 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nov 6, 1811; Freneda; from F. Somerset; to Lt. Col. Arbuthnot, 8224 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nov 6, 1811; Lisbon; from Major Williams; to Marshal Beresford, 8223 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nov 8, 1811; Eloas; from Major Tulloh; to Lt. Col. Arbuthnot, 8222 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nov 9, 1811; Freneda; from F. Somerset; to Lt. Col. Arbuthnot, 8221 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nov 18, 1811; Freneda; from F. Somerset; to Lt. Col. Arbuthnot, 8220 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Feb 7, 1813; Freneda; from F. Somerset; to Marshal Beresford, 8219 (Box 1, Folder 1)